<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some addition to a former paper, entituled, A short declaration of the purpose and decree of the everlasting counsel of Gods heavenly host concerning His royal seed, to demonstrate the nobleness of its operation, and how God doth manifest it : and is an answer in short to a question as followeth : How God doth manifest this noble and honourable seed in man, in which is the glory of it magnified by its own workings, in all that believe, to their justification, salvation, and to the condemnation of them that resist? / by a lover ot it, and one who waits for its exaltation over all, and hath travelled and suffered for its sake, William Brend.</title>
            <author>Brend, William, d. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20114</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12116403</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12116403</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29304)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 759:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some addition to a former paper, entituled, A short declaration of the purpose and decree of the everlasting counsel of Gods heavenly host concerning His royal seed, to demonstrate the nobleness of its operation, and how God doth manifest it : and is an answer in short to a question as followeth : How God doth manifest this noble and honourable seed in man, in which is the glory of it magnified by its own workings, in all that believe, to their justification, salvation, and to the condemnation of them that resist? / by a lover ot it, and one who waits for its exaltation over all, and hath travelled and suffered for its sake, William Brend.</title>
                  <author>Brend, William, d. 1676.</author>
                  <author>Brend, William, d. 1676. Short declaration of the purpose and decree of the everlasting counsel of Gods heavenly host.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brend, William, d. 1676. --  Short declaration of the purpose and decree of the everlasting counsel of Gods heavenly host.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54319:1"/>
            <p>SOME ADDITION TO A FORMER. PAPER. ENTITULED, A SHORT DECLARATION of the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and Decree of the Everlaſting COUNSEL of GOD'S HEAVENLY HOST, concerning his <hi>Royal Seed;</hi> to demonſtrate the noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its Operation, and how God doth manifeſt it. And is an ANSWER in ſhort to a QUESTION as followeth; <hi>How God doth manifeſt this noble and honourable Seed in Man; in which is the glory of it magnified by its own work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in all that believe, to their Juſtification, Salvation, Redemption and Glorification; and to the Condemnation of them that reſiſt it?</hi> By a Lover of it, and one who waits for its Exaltation over all, and hath travelled and ſuffered for its ſake. <hi>WILLIAM BREND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Wilſon,</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:54319:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54319:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Some ADDITION to a former PAPER, Entituled, A Short Declaration of the Purpoſe and Decree of the Everlaſting Counſel of God's Heavenly Hoſt,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>OH thou Off-ſpring of God! Who can ſet forth the glory of thy Conception, Birth, and Being, and the Womb that bears thee, and brings thee forth, and the Breaſt that gives thee ſuck, and thoſe Paps from whence thy nouriſhment comes? Thou noble Seed, and Plant, and Babe of everlaſting bliſs; my ſoul delights in the glorious beauty of thy exceeding comlineſs, in every part of thy Body; which art joyned to ſo glorious a Head, which gives thee thy Being in himſelf, who is over all Principalities and Powers; the Triumph over Death, Hell, and the Graves ſitting on the Throne of exceeding Dominion and Authority over all.</p>
            <p>The almighty Power, which is the beginning of the Creation of God, is the firſt of thy Conception; the Father of all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, from the boſom of his eternal Love and Counſel doth this Seed iſſue forth; which is of perfect purity and clearneſs, and uniteth not with any thing of that which defileth: For, that which defileth, riſeth out of that part which ſtandeth in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and in that Nature and Being, which is not of God, but of the Devil, the Father of lyes, and all falſe conceptions, which ſtand in the time of the fall from God, the ſeed of the Serpent, which was brought forth ſince the Creation, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience. But thou, noble Seed of the everlaſting God, who wert before Creation was, or had a being in this Earth; whoſe goings forth have been manifeſted in time, though thou hadſt thy Being in God before all time; who wert, and art the Fathers delight, becauſe it was from his own loynes, and boſom of his eternal Love.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54319:3"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How doth God manifeſt this noble Seed in Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> God who is Light, doth ſhine forth by his Son, who is the Light of himſelf, in the hearts &amp; conſciences of men, which are in darkneſs, and covered with the ſhadow of death; which death came upon all men for the diſobedience ſake; &amp; the Light is manifeſted, to ſhew unto men, that they are ſo in death and darkneſs, and ſeparated from God, who is Light; that they lie under his wrath, and are in anguiſh, wo, and miſery, without any hope of recovery, as from themſelves, or any power under Heaven. And therefore this Light is God's Witneſs, ſet in Man, to reprove, judge, and condemn, ſmite, and check that which diſobeys and ſins againſt it; and brings the ſorrow and anguiſh upon the ſinner, as a reward for his iniquity.</p>
            <p>And herein is the free Love of God manifeſted unto the world, that <hi>he hath ſent his onely begotten Son into the World;</hi> who is the Light of the world, <hi>that whoſoever believeth in him,</hi> who is Light in them, <hi>ſhould not periſh,</hi> nor abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life.</p>
            <p>Therefore the way to know this noble Seed, and how God doth manifeſt it in man, is to know, and believe in the Light, that ſhines in the dark hearts of the ſons of men; and as thou comeſt to hearken to its reproof, and believe in that which ſhews thee the ſecrets of thy deceitful heart: It will manifeſt its ſelf in its power, to diſcover unto thee, that thou art not ruled by it, but by the power of the Devil, and the luſtful deceits of thy own corrupt heart, while thou ſtandeſt in the unbelief and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Light; and by the power of the Light of the Son of God, thou wilt ſee and be ſenſible of the ſtrength &amp; power of ſin and corruption; and as the Light doth ariſe in thee, thou belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it, wilt ſee unbelief, and ſin to be exceeding ſinful; and ſin appearing in its nature and kind. And this is the firſt opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Light, after the mind is turned to it, and convinced by it, to let thee ſee thy ſtate and condition; that thou art with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God and Chriſt in the world; which nothing can diſcover but the Light, nor make thee ſenſible of, but the power of the ſame; which is the meaſure of this noble Seed, which God hath ſown: And Light is ſown to the Righteous; and this will bring thee, thou following it, (which convinceth of ſin and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54319:3"/>to receive and love the Light; and ſo in his Light to ſee Light, and to bring all thy deeds to the Light, and to hate thy evil deeds, and to love the Light that doth make them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt; and ſo thy heart being made manifeſt unto thee, and thy ſins ſet as in order before thee, and the Light riſing up in thee in its power, judgement, and condemnation, then thou wilt come to abhor thy ſelf for all thy abominations; and this will make thee cry out, <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> And to ſay, <hi>O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable man that I am who ſhall deliver me from this body of ſin and death?</hi> And there will be a hope begotten in thee, to make thee, in thy ſelf, to wait to know the <hi>Saviour and Redeemer, that comes out of Sion, and turns away ungodlineſs from Jacob.</hi> And ſo thou waiting in the Light, which doth work ſuch an effect as is before mentioned; then thou wilt feel ſtriving in thee, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> the elder and the younger; but the elder is to ſerve the younger, <hi>Jacob</hi> the pure plant, and Seed of the Promiſe, the everlaſting Covenant of God, the Seed of the Woman, which is to break the Serpents head. And the ruffe ſeed <hi>Eſau,</hi> the ſeed of the Serpent, the ſeed of God's Curſe; theſe will war one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another; but the ſeed of the Covenant, and of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, is pure, clean, and juſt, ſingle, and upright, and wars in righteouſneſs; for it is of the righteous God, and therefore wars againſt the ſubtile ſeed of the Serpent; the cunning hunter, ſhiſter, deceitful, unclean, profane, wild, airy, flaſhy, empty, and is void of the knowledge of God; which the pure noble Seed of the Woman, the ſeed of the Covenant of Life, cannot have unity with, nor own any of its wayes, or wild workings; but diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers him, in all his ſtrong holds of ſin and iniquity, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells againſt the righteous Law of God, who is the onely Lord and Law-giver: And that is the cauſe of the righteous war of the Lord God in man; to bring theſe ſtrong holds of ſin and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity under his righteous Seed; and that, that will not that he ſhall raign, muſt be ſlain before him, by his righteous ſword with two edges: And bleſſed of the Lord God for ever, are all ſuch that are entred into this war, and that ſtand faithful in this bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel; warring with the armour of God; which are the ſeveral branches or weapons of the ſeed of Light and Life, which are mighty through God, to the caſting down of ſtrong holds, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54319:4"/>bringeth every thought into obedience to the Light; and this is through believing, which purifies the heart; and that is the Faith, which if it be but as a grain of muſtard ſeed, victory over mountains of ſin will be witneſſed, and a hope will be begotten, and patience, and experience of the working of its power; and this will be as the Anchor of the ſoul, ſure and ſtedfaſt, againſt all the ſtorms and tempeſts, that may ariſe to drive the ſoul to ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack from its God, which is its only ſtrength: and ſo the glory of the Seed of everlaſting bliſs comes to be known, to increaſe in its battels, and wars, againſt all the fruits of the evil and curſed ſeed of the Serpent; and Chriſt's Enſign comes to be lift up, and his Standard comes to be gathered unto, and his vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant diſplaying of his Banner is known with triumph, in the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſo glorious a Captaine of Salvation, which ſaves and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deems out of that vile ſervitude, by which they were kept in by the Devils power, which carried them captive at his will, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every ſin and noyſom luſt. Oh therefore, all, come to the Light in each particular Conſcience, which is the pure gift of God; that by it you may ſee and diſcern the enemy of God, and of your ſouls deliverance out of that captivity, by which he would ſtill keep in bondage the ſoul, and the righteous Seed of the Lord God: but in the Light wait, and watch to ſee him in all his wiles and ways of working, to keep this Light in obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the vertue of it under, that the glory of it might not be known. But, my dear friends, believing in the Light; and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſufficiency of it, Oh it will raiſe out of all obſcurity, and it will ſhine, and diſcover all the darkneſs, and all the ways and works thereof; and it will ariſe in ſtrength, and whet its glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Sword of power, to cut down all that ſtands in the way of it; and he will be known to be as a fire, to burn up all thoſe briars and thorns, chaſfe and ſtubble; for the Light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is as a fire, and his Holy One as a flame, to burn and conſume all that ſtand in the way of it, and nothing is to ſtrong for it; and though the ſins and iniquities, be as pricking briars and thorns, as chaſfe and ſtubble, and all gathered as thick combuſtible mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to wound, prick, choke and ſmother, to darken, cloud, vail and cover this noble Seed and Off-ſpring of Light, by its own power it will ariſe out of it all, and make it all manifeſt to their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54319:4"/>utter deſtruction, as there is a waiting in it; and ſo that appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance being felt and believed in, the further manifeſtation of it will ariſe; and ſo it will be known, not onely to diſcover the darkneſs and deeds thereof, and the oppoſition the Prince of darkneſs makes againſt the Light, but ſet up his judging and condemning power, and his full ſtrength to cut off and deſtroy the Devil, and all that ſtands in the way of his ſetting up of his Kingdom of Righteouſneſs, and Peace in the hearts of men: And therefore doth he appear to ſit as a refiner of ſilver, and as with fullers ſope, to purifie and cleanſe the hearts and conſciences of all thoſe that believe in him, who is the Light of the world; which in the fallen ſtate, and the unbelieving ſtate, are defiled by ſin and rebellion againſt the Lord: in which ſtate all men are in, let their Profeſſion be what it will, till they come to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Light, the Seed of the everlaſting Covenant, freely given unto man, for him to be guided by it alone; which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever comes to believe in, they receive the power and vertue of it, and ſo are acquainted with its operation, and the nobleneſs of its ſtrength, life, dominion and authority; which gives vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over the power of darkneſs: but this glorious victory of the Lamb's power, who is the Covenant of Light, Truth, and Seed which ſerves the Lord, none can underſtand nor witneſs, while they ſtand in the diſobedience to the Light, which ſhines in the darkneſs, which comprehends it not. Therefore, if men would underſtand the manifeſtation of this noble Seed, which is the glory of the whole Creation of God; for from that holy Womb where it reſts, and from whence it came, was the pure Creation brought forth, which was before corruption was; and therefore all the whole Creation muſt be ſubject unto it, and its pure power, and muſt believe in the leaſt appearance of it now, in its reſtauration of all things, as they were in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. Therefore there is an abſolute neceſſity of believing in the meaſure of Light, manifeſted from God in the heart and conſcience: though they be dark and covered with the ſhadow of death, this Light doth ſhine upon them that ſit in darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of death: And it is for this end, that they upon, and in whom it ſhines, may turn to the Light, that by it they may be turned from the darkneſs and death, and ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54319:5"/>might not abide in death and darkneſs, but might receive the light of Life, and ſo come to be acquainted with its power and vertue; that in the Light and Life, they may walk, abide, and dwell; and ſo no more to be of the night of thick darkneſs, but of the pure ſun-ſhine of the clear day; by which they come to be known to be the children of the day, redeemed by him who is Light; unto him <hi>all power is given both in heaven and in earth,</hi> to redeem from the dark ſtate, which the whole world lie in; that do not, nor will not believe in the Light of Chriſt in their hearts, freely given from the Father of Lights, which is their condemnation, which in its day and time hath ſhined upon them; but they ſtill rejecting of it, this Light comes to be put out, as to them, though never can be, as in it ſelf, but it ſhines al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bright and clear; and to ſuch in whom it is put out, it will be known, to be <hi>a terrible thing to fall into the hands of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God,</hi> who is <hi>a conſuming fire,</hi> and <hi>everlaſting burnings,</hi> to all that wilfully diſobey, and reject the Light which ſhined in them; which is a manifeſtation of the glorious Goſpel of the bleſſed God, whoſe ſound is gone forth over all the earth, and his word unto the end of the world: And if this Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt; and ſuch are they that hate the Light, and will not believe in it: And the god of this world hath blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the minds of them that reject and ſlight ſo great Salvation, as this is which hath been ſo freely preached, and declared of, and witneſſed unto, by many of the dear Servants and Children of the living God, in this our day and age in which we live. Oh that men therefore, before this day be paſt, would conſider and return to the meaſure of Light in them, before it be put out, and believe in it; and then they ſhall know that it is not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but ſpiritual, and of a ſpiritual nature, property, and quality, and of the nature of God, who is Light; of which, all that believe in it, are made partakers of his divine Nature: and it is able to teach them all things, that pertain to Life and godlineſs; and to reveal the great myſtery of godlineſs, <hi>God manifeſt in fleſh;</hi> and the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt: And that is the firſt Principle of the Oracle of God, which leadeth unto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead works, to ſerve the living and true God, that made Heaven and Earth the Sea and all things therein: and ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54319:5"/>come to know the Word by which al things were made, by which we live, move, and have our being, even by him who is Light, which is the beginning of the Creation of God, both old and new: And ſo his power comes to be witneſſed, and magnified over all, and his glory doth ariſe over all the works of his hands; the noble and royal Seed, and off-ſpring of the infinite God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing witneſſed to be raiſed up by his power, and that glorifies him from whence it comes; and ſo coming to know this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Light, which is the free gift of God in man, and minding of it, it will bring to wait in the ſilence, to know his voice, which calls to be cool, calm, quiet and ſtill: for it ſtills the raging waves of thoſe tumulting thoughts, and imaginations, and conſultings of the carnal reaſoning, of that part which ſtands in the tranſgreſſion, and would have audience, ſo as to prevail over the charming of the wiſe charmer: Now the Light gives the knowledge of that part, and the ground from whence it ſprings, the nature of the corrupt tree, and plant which God never planted, and ſeed which he never ſowed, but is of the Devil the cunning Serpent; and this is needful for every one to know the nature of theſe two ſeeds; be you wiſe or fooliſh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the wiſdom of this world, which muſt be brought to nought; be you poor or rich, bond or free, male or female. Now the way to come to a perfect knowledge of the two Seeds, which are one contrary to the other, as light is to darkneſs, and death to life, and good to evil; you muſt know that in your ſelves which is as a weight and burthen upon your hearts and minds; and you minding of it, you will know it to be God's call and knock in man, that he may be heard, and his voice known, that ſo his counſel may be underſtood, and the operation of his hand may be felt, and his divine power reſerved to work out all that which is contrary to him; and that wrought and eſtabliſhed in them, which is of himſelf, that he may be known to dwell and abide, and walk in them by his Seed, that thereby they may do his will, and be ſubject to his power, that ſo his power may be magnified over all. Now the cauſe why the way, word and voice, of the Lord God is not known, nor the workings of his divine power witneſſed in men, is, becauſe they mind not to turn into that which ſecretly knocks and calls at the door of their hearts,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54319:6"/>but turn aſide from it, though many times the weight may be ſo heavy upon them, that they know not how to bear it; and the reaſon of that is, the loving of their evil deeds, and their hating and ſlighting of the Light which doth reprove them; and ſo, as much as in them lies, run away from that which would do them good, into the evil, as into jollity and ſome outward vain thing; or into the multitude of outward affaires of the world; that ſo by the reaſon of the noiſe of that, they may not hear the ſound of the pure voice of the Lord God in the wilderneſs, that would make ſtreight the way of the Lord, for his ranſomed to paſs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and to come out of <hi>Egypt's</hi> Land of darkneſs, to walk in the light of the living, on which their eternal welfare depends, both here, and for ever hereafter: And the rejecting, and not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the knock, voice, and call of the Light of the Son of God, which ſtands at the door of their hearts, and knocks, that he might have entrance in, and be received by them into their hearts; I ſay, the rejecting of his knock, drowns many in perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and is the cauſe why they wallow in their blood, even in their ſin and iniquity, and become enemies to God, and his pure way in which all his dear ſervants walk in; which is the Light of the Lord God, and by it they know his knocks and calls, checks and reproofs, condemnation, ſalvation, and juſtification unto life. O that men would hear, fear, dread and repent, and not ſlight ſo great ſalvation, &amp; not trample under foot the blood of the everlaſting Covenant of Light and Life, nor count it as an unholy thing; but that they would turn to the calls, and knocks of the Lord God; and that they would underſtand what he ſaith, <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the door and knock;</hi> and every one that hears, and obeys, and receives him in, he doth come and ſup with them, and they come to be made partakers of his banquets, and of the wine and milk that he hath mingled, and prepared for them, in his own houſe: which houſe of God, none can know, nor the Laws, nor Ordinances thereof, that knows not his voice, knock, and call; and that doth reject it, and will not obey it; when they come but in the leaſt meaſure to know it; as ſome may know it by its often following of them, with Plagues and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for their diſobedience; and to bring them into obedience to the meaſure of Light made manifeſt in their Conſciences;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54319:6"/>And therefore all that have deſires in you, to know the Lord, and would walk in his pure way &amp; path, and would find the reſt which God hath prepared for the wearied ſouls; and that would be delivered from your ſins and luſts, which war againſt your ſouls, and from the Devils power, which is not onely your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but the enemy of God, and of your eternal peace, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs: And therefore I lay it upon all ſuch, and deſire that it may lye as a weight upon you always, and that you may bear it continually; to wait to know in the ſecrets of your hearts, the pure calls and knocks of the Lord there, and turn in your minds to it, to know what it ſpeaks; and be it known unto ſuch, it ſpeaks judgement and condemnation to the ſinner, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, and alway calls to turn from ſin, and from the vanities of the world, which lies in wickedneſs, and to turn to the Lord; that ſo from him they may find mercy, and plentious redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and to feel after his Son, who is Life, and the quickening ſpirit; without which, no man can know redemption from ſin, nor reconciliation with God, and ſo, not peace with him; Nor none can worſhip the Lord in truth, but as they witneſs a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Reſurrection of the Juſt; and the Juſt is not witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but by that Power that kills the ſin, and ſlays the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and then that is known, which paſſeth thorow the death and darknes, and overcomes him, which hath the power of death, (that is the Devil) which is the Life of Jeſus Chriſt, the Son and Word of God; which Life of Jeſus doth ariſe, in the deſtroying of the death, and overcoming of him who is the Power and King of death; then Life is known to rule in man, by the power of him that raiſed Jeſus from the grave; and this quickens the mortal body, and then Life rules, and it treads down ſin and Satan's power under the royal feet of his divine Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who is God bleſſed for ever: Oh therefore wait and watch, to know that which is the weight of God's Power, that it may ariſe over that which lies as a burthen upon the Juſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and that that may be removed, and that which is as a weight and burden of and from the Lord, that it may be known and believed in; and that is it that will take off the weight of ſin that preſſeth down the ſoul: And ſo waiting in the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, ſence of feeling will more and more be witneſſed, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54319:7"/>of diſcerning, to know the one from the other; by which diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it increaſeth in you, you will come to know the movings of the pure power of God, and the weight of his Law of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that you may be obedient unto them, that in ſo doing, you may come to eat the good of the Land; and alſo you will come to know the working of the deceitful part, and the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary part, which is not of God, and it will work in a Myſtery: but as thou feeleſt that which is pure in thee, thou wilt alſo feel a love raiſed up in thee to it, which riſeth from its nature, and growth; then thou wilt watch unto that which is pure, that it may ſtay thy mind, &amp; then thou wilt know a guide unto thy mind; which thou muſt know infallibly in thy ſelf; and this is a ſtay to fix upon, which is ſure, ſteadfaſt, certain, and infallibly true; which is the meaſure of the gift of God, the Light, Life and Seed of his eternal Spirit of holineſs: And this being known and witneſſed in thee, then thou wilt know a ſure, certain, retiring place, to retire unto in all times of need, and this in thee; and herein wilt thou know the Standard of the Lord ſet up in thy heart, and it is to be ſled unto, when the enemy doth aſſault thee, and comes in like a flood upon thee, as he may do, to ſeek to drown thee, and to drive thee from this ſure refuge; But this <hi>is the ſtrong Tower, which is the Name of the Lord,</hi> it being fled unto, and this <hi>everlaſting Rock</hi> being built upon, <hi>the gates of Hell and Death cannot prevail againſt it.</hi> And herein comes the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Renown, of the royal Seed and Off-ſpring of God, to be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, which gives and gets the victory over all ſin, and brings in everlaſting righteouſneſs: And as all ſtand in the Light, the righteous Power they will witneſs, and feel ſtirring in them, which will beget a true hungring after the everlaſting righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, and that by it alone they may be covered, and ſo will wait and watch to have it more and more revealed in them, and ſo to receive it into their hearts; and then nothing more deſirable unto ſuch, then to be covered with the ſame; and the power of it will ſo inflame your heart with love to it, becauſe of the nature of it, which will burn up, not only your unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but your righteouſneſs alſo, and ſo you will come to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with that which abides for ever and evermore; the Life of the Son of God, which will make free from the Law of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54319:7"/>ſin and death; and then, <hi>ſin ſhall not have Dominion over them which walk not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit;</hi> no, nor their righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs they will not glory in at all; for now they are not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, but under the free Grace of God,</hi> which believe in the glorious Light of the glorious Goſpel of the bleſſed God; and this comes to be multiplied in and upon their hearts, and the manyfolds of it comes to be known, and read within; and herein they come to be eſtabliſhed, and ſetled, and grounded, in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Truth, as it <hi>is Jeſus,</hi> though they may meet with many oppoſitions in the travel of its workings; for many and great will be the tryals and temptations, in their paſſing forth of <hi>Egypts</hi> Land of darkneſs, and out of the ſhadow of death, woe, ſorrow, and perplexity; before they come to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Land of Reſt, and Peace, and Quietneſs, and Aſſurance for ever: yet in all the tryals and tribulations they meet with, in paſſing out of darkneſs, to walk in the Light, believing in it, and minding of it, the Power of the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, which is the Light; will be with them that receive the Light, the Witneſs of God placed in them, to be their Leader and Guide, by his Pillar of Fire by night, when it is dark upon them, to ſhew them the way that they ſhould go; or by his Cloud by day, as it will ſeem a Cloud to them, but light to him who is Light to guide them; for they may go too faſt, and be too haſty, therefore he will ſtop them, that they may be ſubject to him, both in their journy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtanding ſtill; they that can receive it, let them, that know what <hi>I</hi> ſay, that ſo all may be acquainted with the motion of God in all particulars, that they may not onely have the Light (which all have, though they be not guided by it) which is the true guide and way to God, and everlaſting reſt; but that they may know it aſſuredly, by the true and infallible teſtimony of it ſelf in them, by the daily exerciſe of it; and ſo the ſtrength they daily feel to be renewed upon them in their hearts; and ſo they will come to know the Life of it, to be an everlaſting refuge to ſly unto, in all times of need, tryals, and temptations; and ſo they come to grow in the ſtrength of the Almighty God, who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got them by his Word and Power, and begun a good work in them by his Light, which hath turned them from the darkneſs, they believing in it, by which he will perfect it unto the end,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54319:8"/>and will carry it on to his glory for ever; and then they ſhall know evidently that he hath wrought a change in them, and hath made and is making their hearts pliable to his holy will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and hath performed and is a performing his free promiſe in them, in making them to be willing in this the day of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, manifeſt in them in the beauty of holineſs, and ſo holineſs becomes a delight unto them; as formerly they took delight and pleaſure in ſin and iniquity, they now abbhor it, and as they took pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, now they delight to do righteouſly, and love God's own righteouſneſs, and to walk humbly with the God of their ſalvation; and ſo they wait upon him, to feel his pure power to break their hearts, and melt them in his preſence, that they may always witneſs ſoft hearts, tender, broken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite; and ſo they feel his Love, which is their Life, ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in their hearts; and this, they minding of it; will keep them always in a ſuitable frame, to do and ſuffer the will of God, and to ſtand and abide in his counſel: And who ever thou art that art come ſo far, let thy tryals be what they will, and though they may come thick upon thee, as a dark cloud, and as a mighty Storm and Tempeſt, and as an overflowing Sea, and Floud, thou feeling thy mind retired in the innocent ſtate, inward, to feel the Power that opens thy heart, and thou feeling the ſprings of. Life ſtirring in thee, and bubling forth into every part, with its refreſhing vertue of the noble and righteous Seed of eternal Life, to riſe up in thee; therein is thy refuge, and ſtay, and ſafe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, and then thou art ſafe, as in the Arms of God; and this is the Law which the Iſles are to wait for, and the Arm on which they are to truſt; and that is his eternal and everlaſting Power, to be renewed upon them day by day, and his Love and Life raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them; and this preſerves above and a top of the ſtorms and tempeſts, and the thick cloud will ſcatter; and the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Son of Righteouſneſs doth ariſe above all obſcurity in them, to the great and exceeding refreſhing and comfort of their hearts, with the Lamb's Power, which gives the victory, and the dominion over all the many tribulations; and ſo they come to be acquainted with that in which their preſervation ſtands, which is the refuge of all the faithful ſervants of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, which are acquainted with his exceeding ſtrength
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54319:8"/>to ſtand by them in all times of need, yea in ſharp temptations, and ſore trials, and many tribulations, that doth and will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault them, both within and without, on the right hand and on the left: He that can underſtand, may read me; <hi>A word to the Wiſe is ſufficient.</hi> But it is, that their Faith, Hope, and Patience may be tried, and that they may grow in the Experience: <hi>For, Tribulation worketh Patience, and Patience Experience, and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience Hope, and Hope maketh not aſhamed,</hi> in the Day of the Lord, which they wait and hope for; which will bring them forth as gold; and that they may have knowledge of the ſame, not onely to have that which ſtands by them in a time of need, which all men have leſs or more, though they know it not, but them that ſtand faſt in the time of trial, to have the certain knowledge by the experiment of the workings of his divine power, that their Faith and Hope may ſtand in God, and not in the beſt of the ſons of men: And therefore it muſt be tried by the contrary oppoſition, yea and by ſomething like it ſelf; and the Almighty <hi>Jehovah</hi> knows his own work, which he hath wrought in every part thereof, from the beginning of it, and how he doth and will carry it on; but this Stone is a tried ſtone, ſure and pretious, therefore he will have every one that are built thereupon, come to the knowledge of it in themſelves, that ſo they may ſtand in the ſtrength of it, in the meaſure received from God, that they may ſtand faithful, not onely to have Faith, but to have the knowledge of it by the tryal of it; that they may know the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of it, and to be full of Faith and of the knowledge of his pure Spirit, that ſo they may <hi>walk in the Spirit;</hi> and then, there will not be a fulfilling the <hi>luſts of the fleſh;</hi> but a <hi>mortifying</hi> the <hi>deeds of the fleſh, by the Spirit;</hi> and ſo the Spirit of God is the leader; <hi>And as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God: And if Sons, then Heirs; and Joynt-Heirs with Chriſt,</hi> the everlaſting Seed, and Covenant of God, in, and with man.</p>
            <p>And ſo they know their Heir-ſhip, by the Spirit of the Son in them, by which they call God <hi>Father;</hi> and ſo they come daily to receive <hi>the Gift of the Father,</hi> which is <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> manifeſted in the Son Chriſt in them, which is <hi>the Hope of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54319:9"/>
            <p>And hereby they come to the knowledge of the Lamb's Power, and Seed of God's renown; the bleſſed Root and Off-ſpring of <hi>David,</hi> the bright and morning Star, the Glory of the Saints and faithful Children of the Moſt High God of Heaven and Earth; which is the Power that every knee muſt bow unto, and every tongue confeſs, to the glory of God the Father of all mercies, who from the boſom of his own Love hath manifeſted this ſo great a kindneſs, and his wonderful power, which doth tranſlate from <hi>the Kingdom of Satan, into the Kingdom of his dear Son,</hi> the Light of the world, and Seed of the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant of Life; <hi>In him are all the Promiſes, Yea, and Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much more might be ſaid concerning the Royalty, Power and Authority, Dominion and Victory of the Renowned Seed and Noble Off-ſpring of the Lord God Almighty; but it may be ſummoned up in this, The Eternal Arm of the Lord God's Power is manifeſted, to deſtroy Sin, and Satan's Power in man, and to bring man into obedience of the <hi>pure Power</hi> of the Lord God again, by which he was created, and from which he fell; the Word which made all things, that is near, <hi>in the heart and mouth; which ſearcheth the heart, and tryes the reins,</hi> and <hi>divides between the precious and the vile,</hi> and cuts off the <hi>vile,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the <hi>precious,</hi> that it may ſerve him for ever in the Beauty of his own Holineſs; without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord, who is <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> for ever and evermore.</p>
            <p>He that will underſtand what's before mentioned, muſt reade <hi>within,</hi> with the Light in the Conſcience which muſt give the knowledge of it: for from the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the working of the Light, Life and Power of God, are theſe few lines given forth; not to ſatisfie the comprehending part of that, which may for a time be ſatisfied with the truth of words, but there is that which cannot be ſatisfied with the cleareſt demonſtration of the pureſt words, that may be uttered forth by the mouthes of the beſt of the ſons of men; which are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54319:9"/>forth for this end, to direct the mind, where, and upon what to wait, and to ſtir up that which is pure in man, that he may come to be ſatisfied with the Life it ſelf, which the Word ſoundeth forth from the Life and from the living Power; ſo that, that which hath been dead, may live by it again: The Soul which is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, no mortal thing can ſatisfie, but the immortal Word and living Power of God, that alone can ſatisfie the hungry ſoul, which is ſatisfied with the Righteouſneſs of God, and with nothing elſe; and to that alone I deſire to be known, and that will reade me in the heart, where the Light doth operate and bring into obedience to the ſame: for which end is this, and all that comes from the ſame Spirit in the ſeveral demonſtrations and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations of it unto the ſons of men, to bring all into the Light, and to obey it, that in the life and power thereof they may live, to the praiſe and glory of his Grace, that Life may be magnified over all; and ſo I have my end.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54319:10"/>
               <head>A few Words more to Friends which are in the Truth, to ſtand faſt therein unto the end, that they may feel the Crown and Dominion of the Lambs Power, now in this great Day of Tryal.</head>
               <head type="sub">Which is as followeth.</head>
               <p>SO all my dear Friends, ſtand faſt in the Truth which you have believed in and received, for it is a day of tryal, and a time of great temptation; wherein the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is exceeding ſubtil, and crafty, and wars in a myſtery, even the Myſtery of iniquity; to drive from the hidden wiſdom of God, the myſtery of the powerful workings of Chriſt, in the ſecret, hidden, and inward man of the heart, renewed by the working of his mighty power. But, <hi>Oh God! thy Throne endures for ever, and the ſcepter of thy Kingdom is an everlaſting Scepter of</hi> living <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> And thy foundation is from everlaſting; and this foundation Stone thou haſt laid in <hi>Sion,</hi> thy beloved Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and that which is built thereupon, is of its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and hath its being and ſtanding in that which was before the foundation of the Earth was laid; the unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable power of the Lord God, which was before any thing was, unto which the changable, viſible, diſſolvable, moveable power muſt be ſubject: Yea, thy own whole Creation, which thou madeſt, which is good, as thou madeſt it, and man in it upright; and thou madeſt it all to be ſubject to thee, and to ſtand in thy counſel, and to ſubject to thy holy will; but the ſubtil Serpent wrought
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54319:10"/>in ſubtilty, to betray the innocent being, which God had made, he being ignorant of that foundation which was in the very ſecrets of God's heart, and which he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in his own ſecret counſel, for man's reſtauration back again into a more ſure ſtanding, than upon any righteouſneſs of man's own; and that man might be built upon the foundation that ſtandeth ſure, and that upon it might ſtand firm; never to be removed from it by all the ſubtilty and ſleights of the enemy, nor by none of all the ſtorms, and tempeſt, and violent floods, and waves of foming Seas that he may raiſe, and may be very ready to go over the Souls: But the Decree being ſet, <hi>Hither muſt thou go, and no further; here muſt thy proud waves be ſtayed:</hi> And therefore now being come to that, which was hid in God before the world was; the great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God revealed in us, which is Chriſt, the great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, in whom we were choſen before the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world was laid, and we are come to that which ſhall abide for ever; when all things are diſſolved, which have done their work, that was to laſt the time appointed: And when all thoſe ſpirits that would draw &amp; rend from this ſure foundation, Chriſt, the light &amp; everlaſting rock; thoſe ſpirits ſhall weary themſelves for very vanity, and ſhall eat the fruit of their own wayes, which will be indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and wrath; and ſhall be ſerapated from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the God of our Life, and we in him ſhall have the victory in the Lamb's power, and authority over all the ſubtil temptations of the wicked one; and we ſhall ſit in the habitation of Peace and Reſt, above all the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations of Cruelty, and over all deceitful workings of guileful Men, in the Dominion that our Captain hath purchaſed for us, which anſwereth the will of his Father,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54319:11"/>which gave him a ranſom for many; that our Aſſurance may ſtand, as it doth upon a more ſure Foundation, and better Promiſes, than that of the Law of Works; that ſo we might not be ſhaken, nor moved in our minds, nor hearts, by any ſlights of the Devil, nor Men, which lye in wait to deceive; They being ignorant of God's righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and of his great love towards us that believe, and hope in his mercy for ever: And in that love, life, and power of his everlaſting righteouſneſs, we can ſee through all the thick darkneſs of this world; and over all the confuſed commotions, and ſtirs of the many Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which are <hi>People, Nations, and Languages of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity:</hi> And that which doth ſee through all theſe, is the immortal Seed, the power of the infinite God, the Light and Spirit of Truth, which gives the victory over them all: Therefore know it more and more, that ſo in it you may ſtand, and be bold, and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, you ſpiritual Warriors of, and in the Lamb's power; and that meddle not with the lower powers of the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this world, which lie in wickedneſs, and ſo act with carnal weapons, the will of the Devil, which acts in wicked men, their wicked ends to accompliſh; in which ſtands their ſtrength and outward force, of the weapons of war which are carnal; but our weapons are ſpiritual and not carnal, which do over come the ſtrongeſt force of all outward ſtrength of Men and Devils: For they war with the arm of fleſh, againſt Chriſt the great power of God; we ſtanding faſt in the Truth, ſhall ſee the Spirit of the Lord will blaſt them all, with his Spirit of patience and long-ſuffering; which is the Lambs power, which gives the Faith and Victory over all, through the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, which is, as I ſaid, the great power, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54319:11"/>and righteouſneſs of God the Father of all things, who is ordained a Light and a Lamp for ever, to light the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, into that ſtate, where there will be no need of the Sun nor Moon, for the Lord God and the Lamb will be their Light for ever and evermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="hymn">
               <lg>
                  <l>1. <hi>HE that i'th' Life and love doth ſtand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall ſurely know Chriſt's juſt command;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And movings of his divine power,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Guiding his actions every hour.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>2. <hi>That Rule alone doth guide aright,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſhew the darkneſs from the light;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It lights him the aſſured way</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That leads him to the perfect day.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>3. <hi>To know the Sun that ſhines ſo bright and clear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And makes all miſty fogs and ſhadows diſappear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Light and Life be known, the Standard of the Lord,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which doth to all his own, comfort and ſtrength afford.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>4. <hi>This is the hand that leads to the moſt heav'nly reſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By which alone all that are led, for ever ſure are bleſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Light which is the Love, that from the Life doth ſpring,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shews us the lovely virtue and fruit of ev'ry thing;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That eye which only can diſcern and clearly ſee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The God and Guide of man to all etenity.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>5. <hi>Which Life &amp; Love ſo freely doth from him for ever flow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His Wiſdom and his Righteouſneſs he unto men doth ſhow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54319:12"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In them, that ſo his glory might unto its height ariſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That they may love to magnify his Name in any wiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who is the author of all good unto the ſons of men,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And from his boſom hath his love moſt freely ſhew'd to them.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>6. <hi>The Son of everlaſting bliſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In whom perpetual reſt there is,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Through th'everlaſting Covenant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Made good to all the penitant,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>7. <hi>Who forſake ſin, which God deſies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(And periods all their miſeries;)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is Chriſt the Light, by whom we gain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Redemption from eternal pain.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
